# Yura Malitsky

## Curriculum Vitae

Department of Mathematics Linköping University s-581 83 Linköping, Sweden ☎ +46 (0)13-28 1401 ⋈ y.malitsky@gmail.com

- 1	r 1		•	
	M	1	experience	١
. J			CAPCITCITCE	

01.10.2020 — **Assistant professor**, *Linkoping Univesity*, Department of Mathematics. current

2019–present **Postdoc researcher**, *EPFL*, Laboratory for Information and Inference Systems, Group of Prof. Volkan Cevher.

2017–2019 **Postdoc researcher**, *University of Göttingen*, Institute for Numerical and Applied Mathematics, Group of Prof. Russell D. Luke.

2015–2016 **Postdoc researcher**, *Graz University of Technology*, Institute for Computer Graphics and Vision, Group of Prof. Thomas Pock.

#### Education

2012–2015 **PhD student**, *Taras Shevchenko University of Kyiv*, Faculty of Cybernetics, Applied Mathematics.

2010–2012 **MSc**, *Taras Shevchenko University of Kyiv*, Faculty of Cybernetics, Applied Mathematics.

2006–2010 **BSc**, *Taras Shevchenko University of Kyiv*, Faculty of Cybernetics, Applied Mathematics.

#### PhD thesis

title Effective projection methods for variational inequalities and composite optimization problems.

supervisor Prof. Volodymyr V. Semenov

description The dissertation was dedicated to the development of new algorithms for monotone variational inequalities and composite minimization problems.

#### Fields of interests

Mathematical optimization

Nonlinear analysis

Machine learning

Variational analysis

#### **Awards**

2015 SIAM Student Paper Award for "Projected reflected gradient method for monotone variational inequalities" (SIAM J. Optimization 25, 2015)

## Scholarships and grants

2006-2015 Government scholarship

2010-2011 Victor Pinchuk Foundation Fellow

#### Publication

- [1] A. Alacaoglu and Y. Malitsky. Stochastic variance reduction for variational inequality methods. 2021. arXiv: 2102.08352.
- [2] A. Alacaoglu, Y. Malitsky, and V. Cevher. Convergence of adaptive algorithms for weakly convex constrained optimization. 2020. arXiv: 2006.06650.
- [3] A. Alacaoglu, Y. Malitsky, P. Mertikopoulos, and V. Cevher. A new regret analysis for Adamtype algorithms. In *International Conference on Machine Learning*, 2020. arXiv: 2003.09729. URL: http://proceedings.mlr.press/v119/alacaoglu20b.html.
- [4] Y. Malitsky. Golden ratio algorithms for variational inequalities. *Mathematical Programming*, 184:383–410, 2020. DOI: 10.1007/s10107-019-01416-w. arXiv: 1803.08832.
- [5] Y. Malitsky and K. Mishchenko. Adaptive gradient descent without descent. In *International Conference on Machine Learning*, 2020. arXiv: 1910.09529. URL: http://proceedings.mlr.press/v119/malitsky20a.html.
- [6] Y. Malitsky and M. K. Tam. A forward-backward splitting method for monotone inclusions without cocoercivity. *SIAM Journal on Optimization*, 30(2):1451–1472, 2020. DOI: 10.1137/18M1207260. arXiv: 1808.04162.
- [7] K. Mishchenko, D. Kovalev, E. Shulgin, P. Richtárik, and Y. Malitsky. Revisiting stochastic extragradient. In *International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Statistics*, 2020. arXiv: 1905. 11373. URL: http://proceedings.mlr.press/v108/mishchenko20a.html.
- [8] E. R. Csetnek, Y. Malitsky, and M. K. Tam. Shadow Douglas-Rachford splitting for monotone inclusions. *Applied Mathematics & Optimization*, 80(3):665–678, 2019. DOI: 10.1007/s00245-019-09597-8. arXiv: 1903.03393.
- [9] Y. Malitsky and P. Ochs. Model function based conditional gradient method with Armijo-like line search. In *International Conference on Machine Learning*, pages 4891–4900, 2019. arXiv: 1901.08087. URL: http://proceedings.mlr.press/v97/ochs19a/ochs19a.pdf.
- [10] D. R. Luke and Y. Malitsky. Block-coordinate primal-dual method for nonsmooth minimization over linear constraints. In *Large-Scale and Distributed Optimization*, pages 121–147. Springer, Cham, 2018. DOI: 10.1007/978-3-319-97478-1\_6. arXiv: 1801.04782.
- [11] Y. Malitsky. Proximal extrapolated gradient methods for variational inequalities. *Optimization Methods and Software*, 33(1):140–164, 2018. DOI: 10.1080/10556788.2017.1300899. arXiv: 1601.04001.
- [12] Y. Malitsky and T. Pock. A first-order primal-dual algorithm with linesearch. *SIAM Journal on Optimization*, 28(1):411–432, 2018. DOI: 10.1137/16M1092015. arXiv: 1608.08883.
- [13] Y. Malitsky. The primal-dual hybrid gradient method reduces to a primal method for linearly constrained optimization problems. 2017. arXiv: 1706.02602.
- [14] Y. Malitsky. Projected reflected gradient methods for monotone variational inequalities. *SIAM Journal on Optimization*, 25(1):502–520, 2015. DOI: 10.1137/14097238X. arXiv: 1502.04968.
- [15] Y. V. Malitsky and V. Semenov. A hybrid method without extrapolation step for solving variational inequality problems. *Journal of Global Optimization*, 61(1):193–202, 2015. DOI: 10.1007/s10898-014-0150-x. arXiv: 1501.07298.
- [16] Y. V. Malitsky and V. Semenov. An extragradient algorithm for monotone variational inequalities. *Cybernetics and Systems Analysis*, 50(2):271–277, 2014. DOI: 10.1007/s10559-014-9614-8.

## Conferences and Workshops

- Online, July, 2020 ICML
- Vienna, February, Abstract "Adaptive gradient descent without descent", Workshop of the Research Group 2020 on "Applied Mathematics with Emphasis on Optimization
  - Cluj-Napoca Abstract "Golden ratio algorithm for variational inequalities", Games, Dynamics,
  - April, 2019 Optimization–2019

    Vionna Abstract "On a new method for monotone inclusions" ESI workshop: Numerical
  - Vienna, Abstract "On a new method for monotone inclusions", ESI workshop: Numerical February, 2019 Algorithms in Nonsmooth Optimization
  - Vienna, Abstract: "Bilevel composite minimization problems", Vienna Workshop on Computa-December, 2018 tional Optimization
- Marburg, Abstract: "Primal-dual algorithm for linearly constrained optimization problem", 4th November, 2018 Central European Set-Valued and Variational Analysis Meeting
  - Bordeaux, Abstract: "Primal-dual algorithm for linearly constrained optimization problem", 23rd
  - July, 2018 International Symposium on Mathematical Programming
    - Malta, Abstract: "Primal-dual algorithm for linearly constrained optimization problem", 9th
  - May, 2018 International Conference on Inverse Problems: Modeling and Simulation
- Chemnitz, Abstract: "Golden ratio algorithms for variational inequalities", 3rd Central European
- November, 2017 Set-Valued and Variational Analysis Meeting
- Oaxaca, Mexico, Abstract: "Golden ratio algorithms for variational inequalities", Splitting Algorithms,
- September, 2017 Modern Operator Theory, and Applications
  - Vancouver, Abstract: "Novel methods for saddle point problems", SIAM Conference on Optimiza-May, 2017 tion
  - Münster, Abstract: "A first-order primal-dual algorithm with linesearch", with T. Pock, Workshop: February, 2017 Shape, Images and Optimization.
- Graz, Abstract: "A first-order primal-dual algorithm with linesearch", with T. Pock, SFB September, 2016 Workshop: Imaging with Modulated/Incomplete Data 2016
  - Tokyo, Abstract: "New Projection Methods for Monotone Variational Inequalities", The Fifth
  - August, 2016 International Conference on Continuous Optimization (ICCOPT-2016).
    - Poznan, Abstract: "Proximal extrapolated gradient methods for variational inequalities", 28th
    - July, 2016 European Conference on Operational Research.
  - Kyiv, Abstract: "A Douglas-Rachford method for best approximation pair for two disjoint
  - October, 2014 *intersections of closed convex sets*", VI International Conference 'Computational and Applied Mathematics' dedicated to Ivan Lyashko.
- Heidelberg, 1 Heidelberg Laureate Forum.
- September, 2013
  - Kyiv, Abstract: "A Variant of Tseng's Splitting Method for Monotone Inclusion Problem", V
- September, 2013 International Conference 'Computational and Applied Mathematics'
  - Kyiv, Abstract: "The approximation of a common fixed point of a finite number of Fejér map-
- September, 2012 pings in Hilbert space", V International Conference 'Computational and Applied Mathematics'
  - Yalta, Abstract: "About proximal algorithm for the equilibrium problem", with V. Semenov,
  - October, 2011 XVI International Conference 'Problems of Decision Making Under Uncertainties' (PDMU-2011).

#### Referee service

- SIAM J. Optimization
- Mathematical Programming
- Mathematical Methods of Operations Research
- Computational Optimization and Application
- Journal on Optimization Theory and Application
- Journal of Mathematical Imaging and Vision

- Inverse Problems
- Optimization
- Optimization Letters
- NeurIPS
- o ICML
- ICLR

### Teaching experience

- 2018-2019 Numerical methods I Teaching assistant
- 2014-2015 Analysis I Teaching assistant
- 2013-2014 Analysis II Teaching assistant
- 2013-2014 Functional analysis Teaching assistant
- 2006-2014 Olympiad mathematics for high school students

## Languages

- Ukrainian native
  - Russian fluent
  - English fluent
  - German intermediate (B1)

## Computer skills

Programming Python language

Other Linux, git, emacs

#### Awards in the national and international competitions in mathematics

- 2008, 2009 Silver Medal, 4th, 5th Internet Mathematical Olympiads for Students, Ariel University Center, Israel.
  - 2008 3rd Prize, 69th William Lowell Putnam Mathematics Competition, Faculty of Mechanics and Mathematics, Taras Shevchenko National University of Kyiv.
- 3rd Prize, 45th and 46th Ukrainian National Mathematics Competition for high 2005, 2006 school students.

## Participation at schools

- Austria, 2014 Gene Golub SIAM Summer School 2014. "Simulation, Optimization, and Identification in Solid Mechanics", Linz.
  - Czech, 2012 Spring School on Analysis 2012. "Variational Analysis and its Applications", Paseky nad Jizerou.
  - Spring School on Analysis 2011. "Functional Spaces, Approximation, Inequalities", Czech, 2011 Paseky nad Jizerou.

#### Social activities

2009-2015 Member of jury of the Ukrainian Mathematical Olympiad (high-school level)

Training sessions for regional, Ukrainian and International mathematics competitions (high-school level)

Member of the creating and selection problem committee for Ukrainian mathematical competitions (high-school level)

2009-2014 Teacher at Summer Math Schools